# **Chase Stokes**

cstokes@ischool.berkeley.edu chasejstokes.github.io

I am a mixed methods researcher situated at the intersection of language and visualization. My work focuses on the challenges and opportunities presented by multimodal information displays, delving into how language shapes the reader's experience and understanding. I aim to identify best practices for integrating text and visualizations and improve the effectiveness of information communication.

#### **EDUCATION**

PhD. in Information Science

2021 – present

University of California at Berkeley

Advisor: Marti Hearst, PhD.

B.A. in Psychology and Gender and Sexuality Studies

2021

Northwestern University, GPA 3.92 Advisor: Steven Franconeri, PhD.

### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Intern Summer 2023

Tableau

Graduate Student Researcher 2021 – present

Hearst Lab, UC Berkeley

Undergraduate Research Assistant
Visual Thinking Lab, Northwestern University

2018 - 2021

Data Collector Summer 2021
Couple and Family Development Lab, The Family Institute at Northwestern University

Undergraduate Research Assistant

2019 - 2021

Couple and Family Development Lab, The Family Institute at Northwestern University

Undergraduate Summer Intern

Summer 2019

Couple and Family Development Lab, The Family Institute at Northwestern University

### **PUBLICATIONS**

**Stokes, C.,** Bearfield, C. X., & Hearst, M.A. (2023). The Role of Text in Visualizations: How Annotations Shape Perceptions of Bias and Influence Predictions. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.

- Bearfield, C. X., **Stokes, C.,** Lovett, A., & Franconeri, S. (2023). What Does the Chart Say? Grouping Cues Guide Viewer Comparisons and Conclusions in Bar Charts. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.
- **Stokes, C.,** Setlur, V., Cogley, B., Satyanarayan, A., and Hearst, M.A. (2022). Striking a Balance: Reader Takeaways and Preferences when Integrating Text and Charts. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.
- **Stokes, C.,** and Hearst, M.A. (2022). Why More Text is (Often) Better: Themes from Reader Preferences for Integration of Charts and Text, NLVIZ Workshop, IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.
- Xiong, C., **Stokes, C.**, Kim, Y. S., & Franconeri, S. (2022). Seeing What You Believe or Believing What You See? Belief Biases Correlation Estimation. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.
- **Stokes, C.,** and Hearst, M.A. (2021). Give Text A Chance: Advocating for Equal Consideration for Language and Visualization, NLVIZ Workshop, IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.

## **POSTERS AND PRESENTATIONS**

- **Stokes, C.,** Xiong, C., & Hearst, M.A. (2022, Nov). Driving Reader Interpretations with Text Annotations in Data Visualizations. Poster presented at Society for Judgement and Decision Making, San Diego, CA.
- Xiong, C., **Stokes, C.,** Lovett, A., & Franconeri, S. (2021, May). Visual Salience and Grouping Cues Guide Relation Perception in Visual Data Displays. Poster presented at Virtual Vision Sciences Society.
- **Stokes, C.,** Xiong, C., & Franconeri, S. (2020, May). Seeing What You Want: Prior Belief Biases Perception of Correlation in Scatterplots. Poster presented at Virtual 32nd APS Annual Convention, Chicago, IL.
- Callahan, C., **Stokes, C.,** & Lawrence, E. (2020, May). Modifying the Relationship Quality Interview for Sexual and Gender Minority Couples. Accepted Poster Presentation at the 8th Annual LGBTQ Research Symposium at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. (Conference Canceled)

## FELLOWSHIPS, AWARDS, AND HONORS

Fellowships NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program Recipient Ford Foundation Predoctoral Fellowship Honorable Mention School of Information Fellowship for Doctoral Study	2023 – present 2023 2021 – 2022
Awards National Merit Finalist	2017 – 2021
Honors Departmental Honors - Psychology Phi Beta Kappa Northwestern University Dean's List with Distinction	2021 2021 2017 – 2021

## **GRANTS**

Northwestern Summer Undergraduate Research Grant (\$3,500)  Visual Grouping Affords Different Comparison Patterns in Visualized Data	Summer 2020
Northwestern Academic Year Research Grant (\$1,000) Variations in Conclusions Afforded by Chart Type	2020
STUDENT LEADERSHIP ROLES	
Underrepresented Applicant Feedback Program Co-coordinated initiative to provide feedback to underrepresented PhD. ap	2023 plicants
NorCal Visualization Group Organizer Organized 6 unique speakers for hour-long seminars	2022 – 2023
Trainings Chair Masculinity, Allyship, Reflection, and Solidarity (M.A.R.S.)	2019 – 2020
Participant Coordinator, Pre-Orientation Program Coordinator Alternative Student Breaks (A.S.B.)	2019 – 2020 2018 – 2019
Programming Committee Rainbow Alliance	2018 – 2019
STUDENT MEMBERSHIPS	
Association for Computing Machinery, Student Member Psychonomic Society, Student Member Cognitive Science Society, Student Member Society for Judgment and Decision Making, Student Member	2021 – present 2021 – present 2021 – present 2021 – present
AD-HOC REVIEWS	
Ocean and Coastal Research Journal of Official Statistics Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (TVCG) ACM Computer-Human Interaction (CHI) IEEE VIS Short Papers Creativity & Cognition	2023 2023 2023 2022-2023 2022 2021
SERVICE AND OUTREACH	
25th Anniversary of the Master of Information Management and Systems Facilitated two 30-minute panels	2022
PhD. Applicant Feedback Program	2022

# Provided feedback to underrepresented applicants

Student Volunteer at IEEE VIS	2022
Washington University School of Medicine Mini-Medical School Panelist	2019, 2021
Alternative Student Breaks	2017 – 2019
College Mentors for Kids	2017 – 2019

REFERENCES PROVIDED UPON REQUEST